At least
Linda Derrick
would be joining us, but I did get a letter from her.
Hope that looks
like Leanne's
phone number showing up there. Is that you Leanne?
Yes.
>> Okay.
Good evening Leanne.
Now are you watching us
online Leanne
so that you can see
what we put up on the screen?
Yes.
>> Okay, very good.
So it's 701,
and I would like to call the public hearing
to order.
The
purpose of the public hearing tonight
And Mindy, are you recording this?
Yes, I am. Okay, thank you. Just wanted to make sure before we started. I figured you probably were.
This is for the application of the Andover Planning and Zoning Commission
to amend section two point one and two point two
to establish new overlay districts in the Andover Lake area
and add section 7.6,
7.7,
and 7.8
so as to establish criteria
for mitigating the potentially detrimental effects
of construction in the defined areas.
This includes
the adoption of map depicting four separate overlay zones.
The intent of this amendment
is to mitigate the detrimental effects of stormwater runoff into Andover Lake,
thereby preserving its water quality.
So
with
that in mind,
again, I'd like to remind everybody that the session is being recorded.
We'll
do the discussion of the map
and then the requirements.
And I would like to have all of the discussion pertaining to the map and the regulations done during the public hearing portion
Because once we go into the regular session,
the alternates,
if they are not seated, and it looks like they probably will not be tonight because we
got the full Commission here,
Won't be allowed to ask questions as we go in to deliberate
after we're done with the public hearing.
So
that's what we got about
where we're going tonight.
And with that,
Mindy, could I ask you to call up the map? We'll go through that first.
Okay,
so if
you could scroll down that so we can get most of
the Lake District in,
that's good right there.
So again, we've
set
we've got the area outlined in blue being the Lake District,
the area outlined in red
being the watershed area.
And then working our way out from the lake itself, we've got the yellow areas
identifying
those in
zone A where we would put the most restrictive
regulations
into effect because that's got the most effect on the lake. We'll move outward to
the light blue,
which is Zone B.
A little bit less restrictive there.
Moving out to the
purple, which is Zone C. Those are the
remaining lots in the Lake District.
The
B zone are the ones right across the street essentially from
the ones on the lake itself. And then those in the
tan color are outside of the Lake District but still within in the waters yet.
So
with that
in mind,
I would ask if there's any questions on the map
per se.
And I don't expect too many because we've talked about it amongst ourselves
quite a bit.
>> Jed, is this the map that we reviewed last meeting? It is, Yep. Okay. So no changes to it.
Good. Well, the red line.
>> Yep.
The watershed.
And again, there may be Susan a slight difference between this and the last map we got
Jim got two copies of the map from
whoever printed them up and we couldn't tell the difference. So Jim called up and asked what the difference was.
And one of them had the property outlines
a little bit darker.
And so I don't know if I showed the lighter outline or the darker outline, but they're identical with the exception, this one's easier to see the delineation of the different pieces of property.
That we had two maps and so that would be the only
reason that I showed a different one last time is maybe I called up the one that wasn't quite as dark.
But I could not tell any difference between them. Any other questions on
the map?
Okay, with that in mind, that was easy.
Pull that down.
I'm losing.
>> Mindy.
And I am going to if you can allow me to
share my screen, Mindy.
All right. You should be able to now.
>> Okay,
so can everybody see the copy of the draft regs
that I'm thinking I'm putting up?
Yep.
Okay, and so the reason that I'm putting mine up
as opposed to the ones that are on the website
is because if we have any minor changes as we go through tonight,
I can make those and then I can send them into
Mindy and Jim and they can
use those for whatever
happens next to make these official.
But if we go,
so we'll start out with sections two point one and two point two,
which essentially added
the Andover Lake Watershed Protection overlay zones A, B, C and D,
And then talks about
the map.
We've
got a little spot here that we'll put in
a map date. I think Jim, you were recommending the date of February 25 for
these being
approved?
That they've given everybody a month to
to comment on it that might want to do so?
Jim?
You're on mute, Jim. I can't hear you.
>> Okay.
No, I'm saying, though, that the amended date,
adopted date would be tonight.
Okay. The effective date would be a month from tonight.
That's what I'm suggesting.
Okay.
>> So just so I understand the area that's in yellow would then be tonight's date.
And this is why? Yes.
Okay.
>> So the draft motion
or the motion
should coincide with what's plugged in there.
>> Okay. And so that's why I wanted to do that. So we got
the date
in the regulations.
And Jim, I forgot to check and look, is the scale on the map that we've got, do you know if it's the one inch equals 500 feet?
Oh, I don't
>> know. Okay.
I'll let you check that. That was the one detail in there that I thought
might have been problematic if we had the wrong scale, not that anybody would know.
And that said, this map is included as Appendix two. So
I think that
finishes up
the section two of the establishing of the districts here, unless there are any other questions
on that.
Okay, we'll move on down to
our section 7.6.
And
I'll start out with the intent.
And that
I think was pretty straightforward.
We're intending to make
the water a little bit cleaner,
reduce the runoff and that sort of thing. So
if anybody has any questions on that section,
speak up. Otherwise, I'll go to
7.6.2.
Looks good, Jed. Okay,
>> moving down
7.6.2.
I had no comments on what's written here. I'd be happy to answer any questions on that.
Okay,
moving on to the requirements and I did have
a recommendation
on this and Mindy, I have these typed up so that
you don't have to worry about
getting them down. I'll go to you there, send them to you as soon as we're done here.
But when we get into the requirements, it starts off by saying for all applicable land use activities within the Andover Lake Watershed Protection Overlay Zone,
a completed nutrient allocation worksheet shall be used.
And one, know that's not true because we're not going to use the worksheet in Zone D.
And it says it shall be used to calculate whether the proposed change would increase the amount of phosphorus nitrogen leaving the site.
And that's not true
either because we're expecting to have a reduction. We go through,
you know, the reduction in Zone A is 10%, Zone B 7.5%,
and Zone C 5%.
So I thought those first couple of lines there
weren't
what we were looking for.
And so I was going to replace, I recommend that we replace it with these here, and I'll just read it.
For all applicable land use activities within the Andover Lake Watershed Protection Overlay Zones Alpha through Charlie,
the completed nutrient allocation worksheet shall be used to calculate amount of phosphorus leaving the site prior to the planned activity. I took out nitrogen because our worksheet only deals with phosphorus, although if you reduce one, you reduce the other.
The nutrient loading will be used to determine the reduced post activity
nutrient loading requirements by these regulations.
So what we're trying to do is we're trying to figure out what we got initially
and what the final answer should be after we take our reduction.
The amount of nutrient reduction is based upon the respective zones with zone A closest to the lake requiring the most reduction.
Best management practices to increase
the infiltration and or reduce stormwater runoff will have to be implemented to achieve these required reduction, to achieve the required reduction.
So anyhow,
it's,
you know, we worked a lot on
the worksheet and on the different zones and all that and
I think
we missed in this opening paragraph where it talks requirements and I thought we ought to have that being as reflective as we can. So,
comments on that change?
Okay,
so.
I knew that would happen.
Okay, well I'll go through and fiddle with how to make the margins
right after
we get there.
Oh, I guess another
comment before we go any further. One of
the comments we had at the last meeting was
it would be nice if we put all the definitions
up in the front.
And I looked
at doing that and started working on the definitions.
And I chose to leave them where they were
because
my ability to get all the different renumbering after I renumbered the different sections and get all the different things going back to the right one
would be probably
couldn't get there.
And some of the definitions we have there really need to go into section 2.2.
And so
the lesson learned for me is, you know, we got to start with the definitions
right up front going forward to build the new regulations.
But
I didn't stand a chance of getting
this right if I started fiddling with the definitions and renumbering all the paragraphs.
So I chose to leave it where it is. So that's why I didn't do anything with that one.
Okay, Millennial, that's it on the
requirements.
I guess we'll go down to nutrient allocation worksheet to determine compliance.
And
here, you know, one of the things that I wanted to point out,
you know, we
talked a bit about
what should we do with an undeveloped lot on the lake. And there were, you know, three or four different options that we had looked at.
And
what I chose to put in here and what I think we all agreed was as good a plan as any for
the couple of undeveloped lots we have is that,
as you see in the last
sentence here,
in this case, at a minimum, the property owner will mitigate stormwater runoff by capturing all roof and driveway runoff
in stormwater storage capacity.
So that's
what we're going to do if
it's an undeveloped lot and you can't make the improvements in there.
I think with probably,
you know, dry wells and all that, you could get an improvement, but it'd be very hard. And this just makes it very clear
what we're expecting Jim to expect of the property owners when they go out and develop those properties. Right.
So anyhow, that's
that and that's the change
here.
>> Can I ask a quick question, Jed? You bet, Anne. Did you remove nitrogen from the 7.6.3
paragraph? Because should we take nitrogen out of the title for 7.6.4?
>> I chose
not to do that because
we are reducing both of them. The worksheet when we get there only addresses the phosphorus,
but we're really
using that as a means of reducing both of them. We want
to reduce nitrogen and phosphorus, so I felt comfortable leaving both of those in the title there.
Okay.
I'm going to go down it and now we're going to start
with Zone A.
And there were no changes
to this since
we had last talked about it. So,
oh,
guess, yeah, so we had talked about this a little bit earlier today, Jim. And I just wanted to make sure on paragraph two, it says a zoning permit.
And that is the correct terminology and it shouldn't be a building permit.
Are you happy with the terminology zoning permit,
Jim?
I think he
disappeared and then came back.
>> Hi, it's Jim. I you there Jim, okay. Okay, I might for some reason I'm on my phone now.
No internet on my computer.
I lost you about five minutes ago so. Okay well we're down so
>> you probably
we talked about the runoff for the undeveloped lot. Were you listening when we talked about that being to mitigate the roof and the driveway runoff?
Yes. No, I was not. Okay.
>> But again, for an undeveloped lot,
we expect,
you know, because we can't get to the,
you can't improve on a perfection, which is, you know, the wooded
lot there,
the easiest thing to do is tell
the developers, the property owners that they should capture all the
stormwater ring runoff from the roof and the driveway.
And that
will probably
not make all the people developing new lots
happy
but one of the things I found out as
we were going through there trying to understand these is
the people who have to do something
aren't as happy with them as all the other people on the lake.
And know Alma and Alcoa would prefer that we
have more restrictive measures in place. So I think we've got a good balance there.
>> Should I say something about impervious surface?
Well, know that
roof and driveway are impervious, but what if they add some
additional impervious surface?
>> I think
I don't know.
Put
those words there because that's
what you recommended.
And I think that is
when we went through various examples,
mitigating the roof and the driveway was
a pretty significant
contribution there. It is. And so
I was happy capturing that on those one or two
new lots. And one of the goals here is to keep
it simple,
keep it effective,
and
didn't want to get too much harder
than that.
With the one new lot, you know, we're getting pushed back. The people didn't want to mitigate that. They were giving us all kinds of rationale for,
you know, running down towards the road, not to the lake. And
as I look there, you know, it it the torturous path that it does take before it gets to the lake does allow a lot of time for runoff.
Okay. That's fine then. Yeah, I think there's only two or three lots that this will apply to.
And my goal is to get the
regulations into effect before the people with that lot there might come
to Jim with his building permit request.
So anyhow, that's why that's there.
But now, Jim, my question to you is, paragraph two on the overlay here, is the right word a zoning permit or a building permit here for
not be issued unless a nutrient allocation worksheet is submitted?
How about can we just use zoning compliance?
Zoning compliance?
>> Yes, stay away from the word permit.
Can we say,
I've lost the screen here.
>> Do you have a copy of the regs with you?
I don't.
>> Says the zoning permit shall not be issued unless a nutrient allocation worksheet is submitted and approved for the site surface area. That's
>> fine, that's fine. Zone permit is part and parcel to the building permit. Okay, very good.
>> Any other questions on where we're discussing
Zone A?
Okay, moving down to Zone B.
Again,
nothing's changed from before. Instead of 100 square feet, now we're worried about 200 square feet, a little further away from the lake, a little less restrictive,
and we're going down to
7.5%
reduction
as opposed to 10%.
Okay,
then I'll go to zone
C.
And here we've changed,
you know, instead of 100 or 200, we go to 300.
In
the amount
of reduction, we're looking at a 5%
less.
And that's it.
Going on to Zone D, no nutrient allocation worksheet required.
We
do expect to infiltrate a two inch flush from whatever the increased impervious
area is
and
that's it for Zone D. Nothing's
changed there since we talked about that before.
Okay, 7.6.9
just talks about
not every runoff coefficient in the world is listed on our worksheet.
If they have some basis for some different
thing than what we've got there,
Jim's willing to entertain
that.
Moving on to 7.6.10,
this is the
one time small surface change which is
if we're doing an area less than 100 for A, 200 for B, 300 for C,
Jim can
do
a little rain garden or a trench filled with stone and
you know, it talks about the dimensions there and
just mitigate it that way.
Okay,
7.6.11
is
best management practices.
No changes there from what we had talked about before.
Was your question?
Nope? Okay.
Modification of lake watershed by special permit. So if somebody thinks that they can't
comply with our nutrient allocation worksheet requirements,
And I think that's a pretty tough sell that they wouldn't be able to do that. They may not want to be able to do that, but that's a different matter.
They
can come to the Commission
with a special permit.
And this has the requirements that we would
expect to be satisfied
before
we grant that special permit.
And again, that's not an awful lot of
reduction in what they would be doing by the nutrient alloy worksheet.
Happy there.
Next section is if the property is not within the Andover Lake watershed,
you know,
can come talk to Jim. He can check the map, check
them with them and if he agrees that it's not in the watershed, they
don't have to comply by these requirements
And
does, since that's a determination
that would have to be put in the paper so everybody can see it so that
if somebody doesn't like that decision, they can go back and
appeal it.
Okay, so that is
everything to do with
stormwater
runoff.
There was one thing that I hoped I was planning to call up and
it either slipped my mind or I didn't see it and I'll just see if I can come up with it.
Somewhere here in the undeveloped
lot,
I thought I put in some words to
allow
Jim to give a guy credit
things that he had done previous to putting in his new plan.
Don't see him right this minute,
but
I certainly think that we want to encourage all the property owners to take action to
improve,
mitigate the runoff. And if they were to do that and then wanted to make some improvements,
Jim would consider that
okay. I don't
see it in there, but I think it's probably.
Okay, yep. Here it is up here under the intent. And
you know, one, property owners are encouraged to implement additional stormwater mitigation. If they're out there building a house,
that's the ideal time to,
you know, put in dry wells and that sort of thing,
why they're doing it, and we would encourage them to do those kind of extra
actions. And then the last paragraph here talks about actions taken by property owners
may be considered in fulfilling future measures required by further future development so that
that allows the good citizens to get a little bit of credit for any good work they did. So that covers all the points that I wanted to about stormwater runoff.
We're ready to move into
septic
changes
here.
And I got a little bit of feedback from our
town's sanitarian
fad king today.
So
when we get there, I'll talk about what he suggests. I think it's
pretty easy. But
the intent and purpose
talks into our
small lots,
old septic systems.
It says the majority of septic systems were installed prior to 1980. And
I was always curious what the magic date of 1980 was. Maybe septic tanks wear out after forty years, I don't know. But
it turns out that
around 1980,
maybe 1982,
is when the state's
septic tank public health codes were put into effect.
And so when I was talking with Thad King about
the goals for our regulations
here,
He was just wanting to make sure that we weren't going to get everybody a new septic system overnight.
He said that either in his health district or the entire state, I can't remember,
are 20,000
septic tanks right now,
and probably
only 10,000
of those do they have any documentation
of
to know whether or not they're in compliance with the rules that have come into effect. So they've been working
on that since 1980,
and they're about halfway there now.
I thought it was interesting,
you know, we can
make requirements
that are more significant than the public health code
if we want.
He mentioned, you know, the state of Massachusetts,
if somebody sells a piece of property up there
and the septic system doesn't meet the existing code,
that has to be remediated
for the sale of the house. And Connecticut doesn't require that, but
there you go.
Okay. So now we get in and
was there?
I know sometimes
with email
system I'm using, I'll try to forward something out and it's not the original thing coming in and I don't get the attachment sent out to everybody.
Did anybody
get
the letter I got from Thad King today?
Yes.
Who said yes?
Leanne.
>> All right, Leanne.
Okay, so at least it went out. Whether or not it was late in the day that I sent that out.
Miracle
of miracles. So
here's the letter I got.
I
think
it implements
pretty easily.
I'll read it out loud
because that gives me time to think you guys can read
and listen at the same time.
So the section 7.7.2,
which is Andover Lake A Zone,
states that a principal structure shall be required to install septic system approved by Eastern Highlands Health District complying with
Connecticut state code.
You can see your ebook. It lists the conditions.
>> And
then the next paragraph he says, the local director of health may require expansion of the existing sewage disposal system or installation of new sewage disposal system at the time of the change in use
of those properties whenever the proposed change in use results in more than 50% increase in design flow. And design flow seems to be the buzzword that he was looking for.
And it talks about design flow means the anticipated daily discharge from a building is determined in accordance with
some other tech standards.
And it goes on to discuss what the design flow is for various bedrooms of houses there.
So I think what he's telling me is to take the paragraph
that
we had there and just add the words
when the project design flow exceeds 50%
and these four
items down here,
and then
this one, you know, number five replaces
the
seven items that we had
that
were in there.
And so based on his recommendation,
I was just going to
add when the project design flow exceeds 50% to the title,
conditions requiring a new appropriate upgraded septic system
when the project design flow exceeds 50%.
And then
take out our
seven things and put his four in
there
or five rather.
>> Okay, I have a question.
How were our seven developed? Did we do those or were those John Valentes?
>> They were
John Valentes
And again, we borrowed the
regulations
heavily from Columbia's,
but Columbia did not have
any
septic system
regulations in their lake racks. And so I don't know if he made these up or came through,
you know, he got them from someplace else, I've got no idea.
I do know that we talked
about it a lot and the goal
is to
get all these outdated,
not compliant septic systems to meet state code today.
>> Okay.
Thad or someone from his
agency would be the person who would be permitting
the septic tank? Yes.
Okay.
That being the case, that makes a lot of sense, what you're saying. Yep.
>> And again,
as we develop these, we spent some time talking about
is the right height above the water table 12 inches or 18 inches. We started out with 12.
We increased that to 18 inches above the water table
to be
more restrictive,
but also consistent
with the Connecticut Health Code. Why don't we we're around the lake. Why don't we expect
a septic system to be full compliance with code? And so we changed that. We stuck with the 50%
size thing because that's consistent with the health code. So
essentially, we're just saying
we want it to meet
the health code.
And if you think it meets the health code, you get your professional engineer out there
and do some testing and certify to us that it is. Now,
as I wrestled with myself over, okay, so the guy, somebody
put in a new septic system approved by public health a year ago, and we have all the documentation we need over in the town hall.
Do we need to go out and get the professional engineer to
recheck that?
And I think we probably don't, and I think Jim can probably
determine,
you know, when
he needs to do that. He's certainly, you know, way more knowledgeable on the septic system
repairs and regulations than I am and working
with that king,
they'll come up with the right answer.
So I was happy with that.
If Jim's got any questions, can make the guy go out and get the professional engineer in there. But to take that cost,
if we have
all the documentation we need and it was just put in recently,
I think that's
more than we could hope for. We really want to get the outdated non compliant septic systems fixed.
And so, you know, his second paragraph of the letter, same recommendations apply to section 7.7.3.
So I guess what I didn't do because I got there late is if we had seven and he's got five,
what did he get rid of?
Because he still has
And I guess we're getting rid of when the net floor area of a principal building increases by 20%.
And I'm okay with that because really, you know, the thing that allows more people to live there is more bedrooms and that sort of thing.
And even then, Thad left in
when one or more bedrooms are added, which would require the B100 approval from Connecticut Public Health anyhow. So two is already kind of a duplicate of one, and he left that one in there. So I guess we're good to go.
Okay.
I'm going to
so we're back to
the septic system words.
Here's for zone B. Those are the only two
that it has.
We've got some voluntary
actions beneficial to the lake
that aren't part of the requirement,
but when somebody's putting in a new septic system,
the inland wetlands folks could ask a couple of these things and that might be nice. Then
7.8
has got definitions that we had talked about last time.
So that is
all
that I have to say about the lake regs.
I would point out for
the public record,
if anybody didn't see it, we did get
I got a
letter emailed to me from Andover Lake Management
Association Board
that's supportive.
I'm not going to go through
and
read the whole thing. It does talk about the fact that
we have, you know, had our limnologist going out there sampling and
it looks like the algae growth in the lake is headed the wrong direction, not as bad as it was some twenty years ago after we had fixed up some septic systems. Since then it went down, but it's coming back and they
appreciate the efforts that were taken to do that. So
the two other things I wanted to make sure were in the record
were the letter we got from Alma
saying the Alma and Alcoa board
concur with
the regulations
and the changes
suggested by Thad King
that I will put in before I send these back
to Jim and Mindy.
Any other comments on
the late Gregs? Going once,
going twice.
I have a question.
Yep.
>> When does CROG come back to us about the regulations?
>> So
we
I don't know if they will. Jim, did you ever get a hold of anybody there today on that?
I know Jim was trying to get a hold of somebody over at Crogg. Didn't. We have given him the requisite amount of time.
Jim did get ahold of
the people over in
and Hebron, which are the two towns that are in the watershed, just so they were aware of what we were doing. And they did not have any comments on it. And so
by virtue of the fact that those two towns who
are not even affected by it but
might be interested in what we're doing
didn't have any comments and we didn't hear anything back from Crogg
and we met the time requirement, I thought we were good to go. That's fine. I just wanted to make sure for the record that
we knew that. Yep. Okay. Very good. I appreciate the backup.
Okay. I'm going to stop sharing.
And
at that point,
Jim, are you still with us?
Okay, I see your microphone flashing on and off there, Jim.
Can you hear me now? I can hear you now Jim, yep.
>> Oh, it
says done speaking. Okay.
Yes, I'm up. I'm
>> here. Okay, so my question,
I see no reason
to
not close the public hearing at this point.
Can you think of any? No, I cannot. Okay,
So
given that, I would request a motion
that we
close the public hearing.
I'll motion to close the public hearing. Thank you, I have a second. Thank you, Susan. I have a second. Yep. Got you, Susan.
Any discussion?
Okay.
With that,
I'm going to do a roll call just because
I'm not sure of the process for doing a unanimous one
here. But I'll start with Anne.
Aye.
>> Scott.
Susan.
Aye.
Leanne.
And I vote aye as well. Motion carries five-zero-zero
and public hearing is closed.
And we will
go find my agenda here
to
Okay,
so the
public hearing was closed at 07:46.
It is now 07:47.
I'll call the regular
planning and zoning meeting to order.
Roll call, I see that we have Anne Cremay,
Scott Bersand,
Susan England,
Leanne Hutchinson and myself all present.
So those are the five regular commission members. We also have present Kevin
Arneson and Anne Blanchard,
our alternates,
and they will not be seated tonight.
The
next item is the public participation.
And I see nobody from the public here.
So we'll move on to additions
and or changes to the agenda.
Hearing none, we'll go on to
old business.
And the first item of old business is the zoning
regulation
amendment.
And at this point,
I'm looking for a motion that the regulations
be
approved.
Jed, would you like to hear my draft motion?
>> Certainly.
I'm just going wait till we get into discussion, but we can do that now.
>> Okay.
All right, I'm gonna throw it out there. Move that the application
of the town of Andover acting through its planning and zoning commission,
proposing amendments to the Andover zoning regulations be adopted more specifically, the changes to section two one, two two,
two three, seven six,
seven seven,
and seven eight
of the end of our zoning regulations and the adoption of the map entitled.
I'll make a correction here. I have on my draft Andover Lake, but if you go to the definitions in
the draft reg, they refer to the map as
the Andover
Watershed Protection.
No, the Andover Lake Watershed Protection Map
is
what they refer to it in seven, second
definition.
So, you know, for the sake of consistency,
the adoption of the map entitled
the Inover Lake Watershed Protection Map,
hereby dated 01/25/2021.
Copy of the amendment is attached to this motion.
The effective date of the change shall be 02/25/2021.
Basis for approval, Post amendment will provide the town an additional tool
to preserve the quality, the water quality of the Andover Lake, which is the goal of the town's plan of conservation and development.
And just
for information,
there's no magic date about February 25. It's a month for tonight.
It gives time to advertise
the action and appeal, the appeal period.
It's not exactly a month, it's less than a month, but
just
I've generally done that as a matter of course, just to, for
consistency, just to keep it easy.
>> Okay, on your draft Jim,
it said it referred to section 2.3.
Yeah.
I don't think there is any 2.3.
Really? Okay. I don't think there is either.
You're
right. Okay. So,
it should only refer to section 2.1, 2.2.
Okay.
>> Okay,
with that in mind,
in the draft motion,
I'm looking for a motion to
approve
consistent with the draft motion that Jim just read
with the
changes
that we discussed.
>> A motion to
approve
the changes that Jim Hallisey
stated.
Okay. Thank you, Scott.
Need a second?
I'll
second. Leanne. Okay, Leanne, thank you.
Any discussion
on
>> regs at this point? Yeah, this is Jim House. I just want to check and make sure Mindy has this for recording purposes.
It's recording. No,
I sent her a copy.
Yep, I got it. The draft.
>> I got it. Okay, all right. Just, I wanted to make sure that you could, you were able to
use She
removes that 2.3.
Yep.
>> And you put in the overlay zones?
Yes. Yep, okay. Thanks, Mindy. Yep. So
any other discussion?
>> I would just like to thank you Jed for all the work you have done. This has been a long time
coming, even
back when I was on the Commission before we talked about it. Is wonderful to see it come to fruition.
>> Well, it was funny because I went back, I was trying to
do a little research on
a different issue,
but I went back to the very first minutes that are archived online, you know, over three years ago,
and they were talking about the Lake Regs then. So it
has been a long time coming.
>> I would really I really appreciate what you did also this is a huge
step for the Planning and Zoning Commission to get these lake regulations
enacted finally.
I was worried that they weren't going to be done after John was
gone
and I'm glad that they're all done and I really commend the commission and you and Ted and Jim Halsey and John getting together and getting these done.
>> We're not done yet. We need to vote. Big deal.
So
>> with that in mind, we've got the motion. We've got second.
Well, I guess Yes.
Any last discussion
before we call the vote there?
Okay. Hearing none,
Anne?
Aye.
>> Scott?
Susan?
Aye.
Leanne?
And I vote aye as well. Motion passes,
five-zero-zero.
Now they're done, everybody. And that
was
one of our key goals for this year was to
get the lake regs in effect.
And so I think there's a couple of
renovations in that coming up in the near future and hopefully these will be effective before those
applications
come into town hall to get it done.
Well done everybody.
Okay,
moving on to the next item of the old business.
And it's use of town owned rights of way.
Discussion possible action.
Jim, And did you have anything you wanted to
explain on that one, Air Force?
>> I'd be happy to. I mean, the reason it came to the commission initially is
there's a parcel on Wheeling Road,
which you may recall was basically,
it was left, well, it was created
with the intent of using,
intended
as
the realigned
Wheeling Road,
which was part of the proposed Route 6 bypass.
We all know that didn't happen. Wheeling Road was not realigned. So there's a triangle of land
in front of this parcel.
Meaning that in order to get to it, you'd have to cross
this land, which is now owned by the town.
Was given
by the state of Connecticut Department of Transportation
back to the town.
It raised this issue
of whether they have a right to cross it or not.
And as a zoning agent, I don't believe I have the right
to
grant permission
in front to the commission
for comment.
And that's where I am. Now, having said that,
there's an additional issue,
which is
that
it appears that the land that was given, land in question, the triangle
is now owned by the town,
that is between Wheeling Road and the parcel
in question,
seems to have a caveat on the map where it's to be used for open space.
So that throws another glitch
into the whole
conversation.
So that's all I have to offer. Believe I'd be happy to meet.
If I'm missing anything.
>> Nope, that's good, Jim. And I would only add to that. So I think the way ahead in
the action for the commission will be
first, we will have to
seek
the advice of town council.
And I don't know which exact
lawyer
that would be yet.
But given that it's open space,
is that something that we would be able to grant
>> Right. Crossing with the driveway? And I did get input from Mark Brantz.
And he didn't have a problem with it, but I don't believe he had information
that land was
supposed to be open space. It's interesting. It's not in the
warranty deed, but it's on the map that is referenced.
I
was kind of looking for a conservation easement of sorts, some sort of and
there was no such document that I could find.
So that's all
>> I have. Okay. And I am not opposed
to
making something easy. We don't have to necessarily make it hard. And if
our attorney says that we can treat it like the right of way alongside the road,
that's a way out. We do need to verify that it's consistent with the open space
rule.
And if it is
not allowed because it's open space,
we get that answer, and then the Commission can vote on whether or not we think
it should be allowed
to be
treated
as a right of way
for that. And at that point,
because the lot
owned by the town
surprised me how big it was. It's actually a one and a half acre
piece of property out there, which is
not we got a lot of lots around the lake here that are a quarter acre or less. So an acre and a half is a pretty big hunk of property to be
running across. We can make the determination as to whether or not we think that's the right thing to do. But I want to get a readout from our attorney.
And I guess, Jim, the last piece of that pie is
that we should
go back and figure out who
wants the answer to the question
because they should be paying the attorney fees
that we use to go out and
get an answer to help them out.
That shouldn't be a cost that comes to the town. So I know over in Inland Wetlands, we were going to go out and do a sidewalk on something preliminary to an application coming in. And we said no application, no sidewalk. We're not going to go out and look at it.
We encourage in planning and zoning people to come to us with questions and we can help them get set out in the right direction.
But I don't know who is actually coming to us that wants that answer. But I do think that they should pay the legal fees to help us work our way through the issue to try and help them out.
And I'm not opposed to helping them out. We just need to make sure we do it correctly and not in violation of any of our regulations.
>> And Jim,
when you let
Mark, Branch, or whoever you're going to let
work on this, they have to be given the restrictions that the state
has given to the town also.
>> Whatever the state provide a copy of that map,
which I may or may not have. But there's
>> got to be more than just a
copy of the map. There's got to be the restrictions that the state
will allow for the usage of that property.
Okay.
>> And
again, come through that. It may be, you know, we'll ask if anybody's interested in doing a site visit out there to just lay eyes on the property because I do think this will be,
you know, somewhat of a precedent setting move. There's not going to be a lot of these issues
where we've got a little bit of town property along a road that presents a guy from getting frontage on the road, but
we want to make sure that we're comfortable with what we're doing because
that'll be used as precedent for somebody else, I'm sure.
So that was all that I wanted to cover about the town owned rights of way.
Next item of old business is filling of vacancies.
And
I think
is everybody
is aware
the
town has elections coming up in May.
And
we've got some
vacancies both on the commission
and the one commission
well, I'll take that back. Two commission openings
expire
the end of June. So there'll be two
regular
commission
vacancies
on the ballot.
And then as of right now, there's a
third alternate position that will also be on the ballot.
I have talked
with Leanne.
She is signed up to run again in
the election this May.
And I've talked to Susan
who
is
for a couple of different reasons choosing to not run again as a regular commission member.
And so that
opens up
a spot
where we're
short somebody to go there. So
the question I would ask Kevin and Anne
Blanchard to consider
is if you would have any interest
in
running for the regular spot. I know you've only been an alternate
for a very brief period of time, haven't been seated on the commission, but I consider
the role of alternates as being
is instrumental in helping us discuss the issues as
everybody else. It's just if you're not seated, you can't vote.
But hopefully you will have had your seat by that point.
But anyhow,
if you're interested, I would encourage you, and I do not know
yet
what
political party, if any, either of you are affiliated with, but
we have
Carol Barton is
the person who's in charge of the Republican Town Committee.
And can somebody help me out with who's in charge of the Democrats for the town of Andover?
That's your Magalde Lewis.
>> Who is that, Anne? Catherine Magalde Lewis. Okay, yep.
So
was
recognizing
that I didn't know how to get ahold of her.
Two weeks ago in the River East there was a nice article in the paper that talked about if you want to run for these that it had the contact information.
I tried to get it out of the paper last Friday and that article wasn't in there. So
I'm
a little bit at a loss there, but I'm sure if you called over to the town clerk, they would be able to give you the contact information if
you're
a Democrat and would like to run.
And again, I think both Kevin and Anne would make wonderful additions to the commission.
And we'll go
from there.
And Susan has
said that she would like to continue on
the commission as an alternate but wasn't sure that she could make that commitment to go four more years if she were elected to that.
That
sounds reasonable.
I
really appreciate Susan's got a lot of
the history experience
on the zoning commission and that and to have her input.
I really appreciate. So I appreciate her willingness to
continue on as an alternate there.
Any questions
on all that that I just said, especially from Kevin and Anne's perspective?
I don't have any questions at this time. Okay.
>> I don't either. I did just want to mention though on Andover Connecticut's website,
everybody's term expires currently in June 2023. So you might want to have them update that so they're aware that there will be
people coming up for the election.
>> Okay,
I will check that.
I was working on that just last week, and I thought we had it updated
correctly.
So
I'm not sure what happened, but I'll go back and take a look and see if we can get
the right information on there. We have spent some time trying to get better
information on the website, the bad information off, and
we'll do that. But I do know that
well, actually, what I read in the River East
there we go, another alternate in the making.
But
what we read in the River East had the right information
with
what we were looking for as far as openings on the Commission and for the alternates.
Okay, that's
it on old business then.
New business, I got none.
Item seven is the approval of the minutes from 12/21/2020.
And
I'm looking for a motion to approve the minutes.
I motion to approve the minutes from 12/21/2020.
>> Okay,
Scott and Anne,
you going to second that? I'll second it. Okay, thank you, Anne.
Any discussion
on the minutes
And I had none. I thought Mindy you did an excellent job there. I'm not the best proofreader in the world so if somebody else has some
comments, I'd be happy to entertain them. But
I thought they looked excellent.
Hearing no discussion,
we'll call for a vote. Scott?
Aye.
Ann?
Susan?
Aye.
Leanne?
I vote aye as well.
The minutes are approved, five-zero-zero.
Next item is correspondence.
And
Jim, we're still at none on that? Correct. Okay, great. We're coming up on the administrative report.
Jim, go ahead.
>> Okay.
Active zoning violations,
Wales Road.
Somebody's living in a camper.
Sees and desist have gone out
approximately thirty
five days ago.
Time expired.
I am now working with Mark Brantz on the next step.
Also, I was asked to contact
the health department, the fire marshal, and the building official.
And I've started that process to see if they
have any
ability to act faster. But basically the next step is, is Mark's, Mark's move, and he's prepared to do that.
And
Shotty Mill Road, and I'm coming up with the number here. So
>> on
the violation,
I'm torn here
a little bit with swift
justice
but a recognition that we got people living in a camper in January
and
So I guess it doesn't have to be
you don't have to hurry it along real fast. I don't
I am sensitive to the fact that people
in dire conditions
in that, but we do want to get the violation.
It'd be nice if there was a good solution to the violation other than these guys setting up in a tent.
>> Okay.
Yeah. The road gentleman
put up a utility building
without a permit.
He was notified by both the building official and myself.
He agreed to take it down. I gave him thirty days.
It it's a steel building.
It was intended for a
an RV, went up right on the really right on the property line.
We use very amenable to taking it down.
>> Didn't see a lot of options. How many how many square feet was it?
>> Well, was for an RV. So I didn't go measure it, but it was in excess of about 800 square feet, I think.
So it'd been
well, it wouldn't have been 800 would have been 500 square feet roughly.
So it did trigger a building permit as well as a zoning permit.
Right, yeah.
Jim, you said the zoning official and you
agreed?
Building
official. Okay, very good.
>> Building official sent out a formal
cease and desist.
Okay.
Moving on, I wanted to make folks aware of upcoming
workshop put on by the Connecticut Bar Association.
And I will send out particulars
put out by the land use
division
of the bar association.
And I've been a couple of times in years gone by, and it's really excellent.
The cost is $40 and I did check with Eric
and he indicated that he would cover any costs that we don't have, meaning we have a certain amount of money in our budget, anything above and beyond that,
it would cover out of
this budget.
That gonna be online,
Jim?
It is. It's a webinar.
And when is it gonna be?
>> Okay.
Thought that was March 6 is the date I saw on that. Yes, March 6. It's 09:00.
>> And you do get
a manual
for reference.
And really some of the best land use attorneys in the state are
involved.
I will send out the notice and people can review it. But I will say that I think you have to turn around registration pretty quick.
Yeah, I'm sorry, March 6, 09:00.
What I got in the
agenda is here, it goes right from nine to four.
There's, you know, there's a whole host of topics
that you can see when you receive. But if, if
when you get it, get back to me. Actually, they're asking for please
register by February 15, it says on the on the registration notice. So
if people get back to me, I will I will sign them up and and
can
participate.
>> This is Leanne. I went several years ago, and you're right. I agree. It's excellent.
>> Yeah. The thing about it is, no matter how much experience,
how much time you'd spent
on the board,
you just learned something. Because
pick up on things that maybe aren't done right.
You'd understand some things that you didn't understand
if you
went when you first came on.
That's
just the way we learn. Anyway,
moving on.
What's coming up is,
we should see a subdivision
on property, conservation
subdivision, open space subdivision,
and situated between Old Farms Road and Pine Ridge Drive. It's currently before wetlands,
It is not yet approved.
I just wanna point out that this is, they're coming in under
the open space
provision
in our regulations.
And I would expect an application at the next meeting, but possibly not, okay?
Other than that,
I'm still waiting for an application for an accessory apartment at 129
Gabon Road, which was approved by Wetlands.
They're a meeting back, I believe in November.
Dealing with a number of people
on
free cuts, determining whether lots are legitimate building lots,
seems to be a rush on that. A lot of activity in the spring,
coming
up on the spring.
And that's about it.
Any questions I'd be happy to entertain.
>> Okay, thank you Jim.
Moving on to
item 10 is miscellaneous.
I think the next thing that I'm going to try and have us as a commission tackle will be the sign regulations
and that's chapter 15 of our zoning regs.
The
basis
for the change will be
again
our current regulations
put special requirements out there where they treat political signs as a special category
and
really
all signs
are signs.
And so
I thought, yeah, I'd gotten a copy of another town's zoning regs that were fairly recently modified.
And I was thinking about doing just a cut and a paste there.
But one of the things that I particularly like about our
sign regulations
is they are fairly concise.
And with the exception of these little temporary signs that you would put up during election season or for other various
reasons,
I think
I don't know when the last time a sign
application
or permit
has come in, but it's
certainly,
I think our sign regulations are working pretty well with the exception of that one little thing. And so
rather than
re go to someplace,
somebody else's regulations that are maybe a little more cumbersome,
we'll stick with what we got and we will change,
we'll put a category in there for temporary signs and
talk about that. But if
each of you could,
when you have that leisure time,
a little late reading to put you to sleep at night, go through our sign regulations, I'm sure that will
help you get right back to sleep.
But that's the next project I see coming up. And if we can get a start on them before all these applications that Jim's talking about come here, that would be great too.
>> Jed, this is Leanne. I have a question.
I haven't looked at that lately, but our political signs are completely
different category. I know there was more activity last fall with the pandemic and the early voting and things like that. And I guess the governor authorized
signs because they went up very early last fall. And we used to have some wording that included things like people giving away kittens and
advertising tag sales and things that were included under the it was thirty days.
You weren't supposed to put something up for longer than thirty days. Are you looking to address something like that or are you just looking to make a provision or
switch the content of the political sign language around?
>> So
your analogy with the the kitten signs is is right on a kitten sign and a political sign.
And any other little
sign that tag sale sign would have you. They're all the same and
we can put whatever restrictions
we want on the political signs as long as it's consistent with all those other little signs.
And so we
need to come up with
what we think the right answer is.
One of the inconsistencies
right now between what we have done and what our regulations
say
is that our current regulations
specify
that no signs
can go up in the right of ways
you know, on down on property.
And we are not
in compliance with that. Before last year's election, specifically said
that we could, which was a violation of our
zoning regs. And so
I'm looking, I don't know that we'll be able to get these
regulations
into effect before May
with the upcoming election. I don't know that there'll be a lot of signs with the upcoming election because we don't have money to make a lot of those signs anyhow.
But
I do
I think
for
an election sign, sixty days is about the right amount of time to have it up. And that would specify that
all these other
a builder puts a sign up out front when he's done a job. Sixty days is plenty long for that. But that's the kind of thing that we, as a commission, need to talk through, come up with what we
think the best approach is. And
since the Board of Selectmen
has
a say in what happens on town property, we probably
need to go somehow
get the Board of Selectmen
involved in that too. I don't know exactly how to do that yet. But step one is for us to figure out what we think the right answer is.
Okay.
>> So that's where we'll be heading next.
Anybody else have anything for the miscellaneous
topic?
Are we going to
talk about frontage?
>> I'm not going to talk about frontage tonight.
I did think we were going to go
a little longer.
I I will wait until
a specific example comes up that requires
that
discussion
just to
set the stage for that a little bit.
So
let's say that this lot on Wheeling Road that has the town property
between
that property and the road, so the property doesn't have any frontage along the road.
Is that a problem? And if you look in our zoning regulations,
we don't use the word frontage
very often. We do in real life. If
you look in the subdivision regulations,
we do talk more about frontage. Haven't gone over there to see how much more,
but you would not build a subdivision
that relied on crossing a piece of town property to get to to the road.
Right. And so
that issue will come up. Is
where Wheeling Road is going to be
somewhat of a precedent setter because
there's another piece of property that may come to us that's got a similar but different situation
all that. But on Wheeling Road,
the story is that the state took the frontage away to change the road,
Then they decided not to change the road.
And so we're left with a piece of property with no frontage on the road.
And that's what we're going to have to make a determination on at some point
about can we cross
that with the right of way being that it was given to the town for open space? What
>> I'm saying, Jed, is I'd like to go through the regulations to address
why it isn't addressed.
Why it's complicated,
why
it's not addressed in our regulations.
>> Okay, and I don't want to do that tonight because Right, okay, no, I don't got No,
>> for our next
month's agenda we can talk about it, can't we? Yep, we can,
>> we'll get a little, I'll draw a picture. I'll dazzle you with my
PowerPoint artwork.
I
can't wait.
Any other miscellaneous comments?
>> Yeah, this is Jim Halsey. I just wanna touch base. I mentioned the conservation subdivision,
what I failed to say was there's
language in both the subdivision and zoning regulations that speak to that,
which might not be what you'd expect.
I believe section five of the zoning regulations
allow the
open space subdivision by
either writers or special permit,
Both, I mean depending on the size of the lot. Just wanted to make it clear that there's language in both sets of regulations.
>> Yeah,
the good news is we've done it once before. The bad news is it wasn't straightforward.
Again, if you look at the little lead in article to
what's on the planning and zoning website,
it tells us
and I learned a lot from looking at that little paragraph there.
We have the
authority to write regulations.
And once they're written, we have the obligation to follow those regulations.
Not what we wish they said, but what
they actually And
so
one of the exercises in a prior life that
we used to do was if you think writing procedures and regulations is easy,
just try writing a procedure for something as easy as making peanut butter and jelly sandwich.
And you'll figure out that there's a lot that goes into that, and until you get into it, covering all the bases and actually having what you want done done is
difficult.
But
that's where we as a commission get to decide.
As long as we're not conflicted
with our regulations,
we can decide on implementation
of these different things. So that's what makes us kind of good.
Any other miscellaneous
comments?
Well, I want to thank everybody again for bearing
with us all through the long process of the Lake Regs. That's
a good thing being brought conclusion.
And
we'll see if we can do just as good a job coming up with a non controversial
answer to the signs that nobody shows up when we take it to public hearing
to ask us any questions.
Would
anybody care to make a motion to adjourn?
I'll move to adjourn at 08:26.
Leanne.
>> Thank you, Leanne. I'll second it. Thank you, Scott.
All in favor?
Aye. Aye.
Aye.
Think that
was pretty easy. I wasn't worried about any
hard spot there. So thank you all for attending tonight. Appreciate your help.
Study those sign regs and
we'll
who's
got a calendar for when the next meeting is?
I think we're no,
next month has got another holiday in it, so we're the following week.
February
22,
I think, will be the right date.
Okay,
very good. I think we move to adjourn.
Everybody have a great evening.
>> Thank you, Jim. Thanks again for all your help. Thank you. Thank you. Thanks, Jim. Jim. Thanks, everyone. Good night. Good night.